Register of the Dan Throop Smith papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Dan Throop Smith papers
1935-1982
73039
Hoover Institution Archives
53 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (23.4 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, minutes, reports, memoranda, notes, clippings, and other printed matter, relating primarily to tax policy in the U.S.
Smith, Dan Throop, 1907-1982.
Access
Boxes 49-51 closed.
The remainder of the collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1973.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at https://searchworks.stanford.edu. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1907, Nov. 20 Born, Chicago, Illinois
1928 A.B, Stanford University
1934 Ph.D., Harvard University
1936 Author, Deficits and Depressions
1949 Author, Taxable and Business Income (joint author with J. K. Butters)
1952 Author, Effects of Taxation, Corporate Financial Policy
1961 Author, Federal Tax Reform, The Issues and a Program
1963 President, Tax Institute of America, Inc.
1967 President, National Tax Association
1968 Author, Tax Factors in Business Decisions
1973 Co-author, What You Should Know about the Value Added Tax (with James B. Webber and Carol M. Cerf) 1981-1982 Consultant, Office of Program Development, White House
1982, May 30 died, Stanford, California
Economists.; Taxation--United States.; United States--Economic conditions.; United States--Politics and government.
- PRESIDENT'S COMMISSION ON INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND INVESTMENT POLICY, 1970-1971
  Scope and Contents note
  Minutes of meetings, reports, memoranda, agenda, etc.
  - Reports, minutes, agenda, and supportive documents, compiled for the meetings of the President's Commission on International Trade and Investment Policy (Box 1)
    - Meeting no. l, May 27, 1970
    - Meeting no. 2, June 18, 1970
    - Meeting no. 3, August 6, 1970
    - Meeting no. 4, September l0, 1970
    - Meeting no. 5, October 14-15, 1970
    - Meeting no. 5, October 14-15, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Meeting no. 6, November 12-13, 1970
    - Meeting no. 6, Report of E. L. Stewart, "Import Competition and Government Relief", November 12, 1970. (Box 3)
    - Meeting no. 7, December 16, 1970
    - Miscellaneous reports of, 1970
    - Meeting no. 8, January 27-28, 1971
    - Meeting no. 8, January 27-28, l97l (Box 4)
    - Meeting no. 9, February 24-25, l97l
    - Meeting no. 9, February 24-25, l97l (Box 5)
    - Meeting no. 10, March 10-11, 1971
  - Report by Raymond Vernon, "The Economic Consequences of U.S. Foreign Direct Investment"
  - Comments and proposals by Dan Throop Smith on successive drafts of the final report of the President's Commission on International Trade and Investment Policy
- TAX POLICY ADVISORY COMMITTEE, COUNCIL ON ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY, 1970-1973
  Reports, drafts, memoranda, correspondence, notes, reprints, serial issues, and clippings.
  - Report of the Tax Policy Advisory Committee to the Council on Environmental Quality (Box 6)
    - Draft of, November 18, 1971
    - Comments by committee members on draft of, November 18, 1971
      - Anderson, Charles A.
      - Applewhaite, Eleanor S.
      - Conlon, Charles F.
      - Gradison, Willis D., Jr.
      - Harriss, C. Lowell
      - Pechman, Joseph A.
      - Sanden, B. Kenneth
      - Slitor, Richard E.
      - Train, Russell E.
    - Draft of, December 17, l971
    - Comments by committee members on draft of, December 17, 1971 (Box 7)
      - Barlow, Joel
      - Campbell, Rita Ricardo
      - Conlon, Charles F.
      - Sanden, B. Kenneth
      - Silverstein, Leonard L.
      - Stockfisch, Jacob A.
      - Walker, Mabel
      - Woodworth, Laurence N.
    - Comments by committee members on draft of, March 16, 1972
      - Anderson, Charles A.
      - Applewhaite, Eleanor S.
      - Barlow, Joel
      - Campbell, Rita Ricardo
      - Conlon, Charles F.
      - Gradison, Willis D., Jr.
      - Harriss, C. Lowell
      - Lindsay, David A.
      - Pechman, Joseph A.
      - Sanden, B. Kenneth
      - Slitor, Richard E.
      - Walker, Mabel
    - Draft of, May 4, 1972
    - Comments by committee members on draft of, May 4, 1972
      - Barlow, Joel
      - Cantor, Arnold
      - Harriss, C. Lowell
    - Draft of, June 28, 1972
    - Comments by committee members on draft of, June 28, 1972
      - Barlow, Joel
      - Campbell, Rita Ricardo
      - Silverstein, Lawrence L.
    - Finished report of, February 1973
    - Draft Statements and Discussion Papers Prepared for the Committee
    - Campbell, Rita Ricardo, "Draft Statement on Population and Income Taxation,", December 17,1970
    - "Decision Paper on Open Space,", October 29, 1970
    - "Effects of Changes Under Tax Reform Act of 1969 on Environmental Impact of the Tax Structure,", August 24, 1970
    - "Federal Income Tax Policy and Land Use"
    - Gradison, Willis D., Jr., "Memorandum to Task Force on the Impact of Tax Policy on the Environment,", November 5, 1970 (Box 8)
    - "The Impact of Current IRS Valuation Procedures on Gifts of Partial Interests in Land for Conservation Purposes,", January 8, 1971
    - Knetsch, Jack L., "A Proposal for Changing Land Taxation,", November 4, 1970
    - Knetsch, Jack L., "Proposal for Limited Effluent Charges," with comments from committee members, November 10, 1970
    - "Preliminary Guidelines for Agency Consideration of the Tax Incentive Approach,", July 24, 1970
    - Sanden, B. Kenneth, "Tax Impact on Recycling of Wastes" and "Possible Changes in Tax Provisions Relating to Pollution Control Facilities,", February 12, 1971
    - Slitor, Richard E., "The Tax System and 'Urban Sprawl,'", September 1, 1970
    - Smith, Dan Throop, "Draft Statement on Proposed Tax Energy," and revision, June 15, 1970, July 16, 1970
    - Smith, Dan Throop, "Revision of Draft Statement on Issues in the Use of Excise Taxation to Improve the Quality of the Environment,", July 13, 1970
    - Smith, Dan Throop, "The Tax Treatment of Donations of Scenic Easements,", July 24, 1970
    - Smith, Dan Throop, "Tax Treatment of Industrial Investments to Reduce Pollution"
    - "Taxation and Land Utilization,", August 26, 1970
    - "Treatment of Pollution Control Facilities Under Tax Reform Act of 1969"
    - Walker, Mabel, "Relation of the Property Tax to the Quality of the Environment,", July 1971
  - Correspondence
    - Anderson, Charles A.
    - Applewhaite, Eleanor S.
    - Atkeson, Timothy
    - Barlow, Joel
    - Bogan, Eugene F.
    - Campbell, Rita Ricardo
    - Cantor, Arnold
    - Conlon, Charles F.
    - Coogan, F.
    - Dane, John, Jr.
    - Dean, Joel
    - DeCoster, Lester A.
    - Edwards, J. Rodney
    - Gibbons, Boyd H., III
    - Gradison, Willis D., Jr.
    - Grey, Alison (Box 9)
    - Harriss, C. Lowell
    - Hayes, Arthur M.
    - Herrero, Michael C.
    - Hoge, Francis H., Jr.
    - Hutton, William T.
    - King, Rosie
    - Leighton, Charles M.
    - Lindsay, David A.
    - Lynn, Arthur D., Jr.
    - Martin, John M., Jr.
    - Matuszeski, William
    - Mills, Morris H.
    - Palm, Charles E.
    - Pechman, Joseph A.
    - Ramsey, Norman F.
    - Reese, Craig E.
    - Robinson, Peter E.
    - Rodgers, William H., Jr.
    - Sanden, B. Kenneth
    - Silverstein, Leonard L.
    - Simon, Gerald A.
    - Stockfisch, Jacob A.
    - Strang, Arthur I., III
    - Train, Russell E.
    - Ulin, Robert P.
    - Walker, Mabel
    - Weidenbaum, Murray L.
  - Correspondence of Other Committee Members
  - Office File
    - Notices to committee members, rosters of committee members, etc.
    - Minutes, notes, etc., of committee meetings
      - Meeting of, April 6, 1970
      - Meeting of, May 5, 1970
      - Meeting of, September 25, 1970
      - Meeting of, November 30, 1970
    - Memorandum by Russell E. Train on Tax Policy
      - Task Force, with comments by, May 26, 1970
      - Alison Grey, and Harris, June 10, 1970
      - Weinstein, June 12, 1970
    - Notes, clippings, and miscellanea
  - Reports, reprints, and serial issues used by the committee for background information
    - Reports by the National Industrial Pollution Control Council
    - Miscellaneous reports, reprints, and serial issues
    - Miscellaneous reports, reprints, and serial issues (Box 10)
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1959-1981
  Bibliographies, biographical sketches, and clippings.
  - Bibliographies (Box 11)
  - Biographical sketches
  - Clippings and publicity
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1935-1982
  Draft and published copies, with associated correspondence and notes.
  - 1935-1940 (Box 11)
  - 1941-1953 (Box 12)
  - 1954-1958 (Box 13)
  - 1958-1962 (Box 14)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 15)
  - 1965-1967 (Box 16)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 17)
  - 1969-1972 (Box 18)
  - 1972-1974 (Box 19)
  - 1974-1976 (Box 20)
  - 1977-1982 (Box 21)
- BUSINESS TAXATION CASE FILE, 1948-1972
  Business school case studies
  - Business Taxation Case File, 1948-1972 (Box 22)
  - Business Taxation Case File, 1948-1972 (Box 23)
- INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS CASE FILE, 1953-1976
  Business school case studies, and other curricular materials.
  - International Business Case File, 1953-1976 (Box 23)
  - International Business Case File, 1953-1976 (Boxes 24-25)
  - International Business Case File, 1953-1976 (Box 26)
- U.S. DEPARTMENT OF THE TREASURY OFFICE FILE, 1956-1958
  Memoranda, position papers, statistics, and telephone logs.
  - General (Box 26)
  - Dividends
  - Memoranda to the Secretary of Treasury
  - Position statements (Box 27)
  - Statistical base book
  - Telephone log
  - American Council for Capital Formation
  - American Council for Capital Formation (Box 28)
  - Canadian taxation
  - Capital gains
  - Carryover of basis on inherited property
  - Citibank Monthly Economic Letter (Box 29)
  - Charitable contributions
  - Comments on The Age of Uncertainty
  - Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs
  - Corporate taxation
  - Costs and benefits of environmental control
  - Deferred taxes
  - Depreciation
  - Distorted language
  - Dividends
  - East-West trade (Box 30)
  - Effects of taxation
  - Egalitarian articles
  - Executive compensation
  - Foreign business income
  - General Motors Corporation (Box 31)
  - Impact of inflation on profits and equity capital
  - Inflation
  - Instituto Centroamericano de Administracion de Empresas
  - Instituto de Estudios Superiores de la Empresa
  - International Trade and Investment, Commission on
  - Limits to growth
  - 1980s project (Hoover Institution)
  - Obsession with progression
  - Organization for European Economic Cooperation
  - Petrodollars, Impact of
  - Population growth
  - Puerto Rico
  - Quotations
  - Reagan-for-President Committee
  - Task Force on Business Taxation
  - Tax-free rollovers of reinvested capital gains (Box 32)
  - Tax policy
  - Tax research grant - Sloan Foundation
  - Tax revision
  - Taxes, price indexes, and inflation
  - U.S. Army Air Forces Statistical School
  - Value-added tax
- OVERSIZE MISCELLANY, 1954-1981
  - Oversize Miscellany, 1954-1981 (Box 33)
- CORRESPONDENCE, ALPHABETICAL, 1960-1982
  - General, 1961-1981 (Box 34)
  - American Council for Capital Formation, 1977-1979
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1977
  - Anderson, Martin, 1981
  - Arthur Young and Company, 1978
  - Baker, John C., 1978
  - Bank of America, 1978
  - Bechtel Corporation, 1978
  - Bergsten, C. Fred, 1979
  - Berney, Robert E., 1979
  - Boskin, Michael, 1977-1979
  - Brookings Institution, 1976
  - Burress, Richard T., 1977-1979
  - Byrd, Harry F., Jr., 1978-1979
  - CML Group, 1978-1979
  - California Institute of Technology Population Program
  - Campbell, Rita, 1974-1979
  - Chiswick, Barry R., 1977
  - Citibank, 1978-1979
  - Coe, Robert P., 1979
  - Collins, Donald A., 1979
  - Commonwealth Edison Company, 1977-1979
  - Conable, Barber B., Jr., 1978-1979
  - Congress, U.S., 1968-1970
  - Crumbine, Peter J., 1979-1981
  - Davis, Paul H., 1978 (Box 35)
  - Data Resoures Company, 1979
  - Eberle, William D., 1979
  - Edwards, John, 1978
  - Exxon Corporation, 1974-1978
  - Federal Reserve Board, 1978
  - Feldstein, Martin, 1979-1980
  - Fiscal Policy Council, 1979
  - Ford, Gerald R., 1978
  - Friedman, Milton, 1977
  - Fritchey, Clayton, 1978-1980
  - Gradison, Willis D., Jr., 1977-1978
  - Greenwald, Douglas, 1979-1980
  - Griffin, Robert P., l978
  - Hansen, Clifford P., 1978
  - Harriss, C. Lowell, 1978
  - Harvard Business School, 1977-1978
  - Hayakawa, S. I., 1978-1979
  - Hefner, Robert A., III, 1978
  - Hewlett-Packard Company, 1977-1978
  - Higby, Norman P., 1978-1979
  - Howell, James E., 1979
  - Hudner, Phillip, 1979
  - Humphrey, George M., 1963-1968
  - Institut Europeen d'Administration des Affaires, 1966-1979
  - International Business Machine Company, 1978
  - Law and Contemporary Problems Program, Duke University Law School, 1977-1978
  - Lenches, Elizabeth T., 1979
  - Lodwick, S. G., 1978-1980
  - Long, Russell B., 1965-1979
  - Los Angeles Times, 1978
  - McCloskey, Paul N., 1974-1981
  - Martin, Thomas A., 1978-1979
  - Mills, Wilbur D., 1961
  - Moore, W. Henson, 1979
  - Morgan Stanley and Company, 1979
  - Munn, James S., 1981
  - National Foreign Trade Council, 1978-1980
  - Packwood, Robert W., 1977-1978 (Box 36)
  - Pan American World Airways, 1978-1979
  - Penick, William C., 1979-1980
  - Pollock, Oscar S., 1979-1981
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1978-1979
  - Renshaw, John P., 1977
  - Republican National Committee, 1977
  - Rockefeller, David, 1964
  - Sanden, B. Kenneth, 1972
  - Simon, William E., 1976
  - Staar, Richard F., 1974-1981
  - Stern, Michael, 1979
  - Sutherland, William A., 1977-1979
  - Tax Analysts and Advocates Company, 1977-1978
  - Tax Foundation, 1978-1980
  - Treasury, U.S. Department of the, 1960-1979
  - Ture, Norman, 1981-1982
  - Uhler, Lewis S., 1973
  - Ullman, Albert C., 1977-1979
  - U.S. News and World Report, 1979
  - University of California, 1978
  - Vogel, Horst A., 1976-1979
  - Wall Street Journal, 1978-1982
  - Wallich, Henry C., 1977-1982
  - Washington Post, 1978
  - Weinberger, Caspar, 1981-1982
  - Wormser, Felix, 1978
  - Zuckert, Eugene M., 1978-1980
- CORRESPONDENCE, CHRONOLOGICAL, 1962-1979
  - 1962-1965 (Box 37)
  - 1967-1968
  - 1970-1972 (Box 38)
  - 1974-1976
  - 1979
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1970-1982
  - Speeches and Writings, 1970-1982 (Box 39)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1956-1982
  Speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, clippings, and other printed matter.
  - Cabinet Council (Box 39)
  - Capital gains
  - Congressional committee publications on tax revision
  - Deferred taxes
  - Earned income
  - H.R. 7015
  - International Fiscal Association
  - Kowitz, Patricia E.
  - Low bracket [of taxation] burden fallacy (Box 40)
  - Marriage penalty [in taxation rates]
  - Percentage changes [in taxation rates]
  - Profits and inflation
  - Republican Party
  - Rollover of reinvested capital gains, Tax-free
  - Rollover of reinvested capital gains, Tax-free (Box 41)
  - Santa Cruz, University of California at
  - Tax treatment of charitable and religious organizations, International
  - Value-added tax
  - Wallich, Henry C.
  - Washington staff seminars (Hoover Institution)
- MISCELLANY, 1979-1981
  - Miscellany, 1979-1981 (Box 41)
- Unsorted materials (Boxes 42-48)
- CLOSED (Boxes 49-51)